[music]
>> I don't know about you,
but it would seem to me
that every morning
that I wake up,
I seem to be dealing
with one crisis after another.
Either it is somebody needing financial
assistance,
or it is somebody who is not well,
needing some kind of assurance and help,
or it is a personal crisis
that I'm dealing with
regarding the ministry,
regarding the work that I do, or even a
family crisis.
Chances are you are familiar with that
scenario.
You wake up in the morning,
and you immediately find yourself
engaged in the process of solving one
problem after another.
Some of the problems may be
small, tiny problems that could be
solved perhaps in an instant.
And then maybe others
seem to be unsurmountable,
and they seem to over-
whelm you,
and perhaps even
feel as if they're crushing you. You
don't know how you can get over them.
Those problems can come to you at a
personal level.
The crisis can come to you at a family
level,
or they may go beyond the boundaries of
the family into your community,
sometimes they hit us at national levels
with prices of gasoline and petrol going
up, or an international level
in situations like the Ebola virus that
we are dealing with today.
And the question we ask ourselves
is,
how do we navigate through the crisis
that afflict us
almost on a daily basis? How do we live
not only through the crisis,
but gain victory
and triumph
over them?
The passage we are looking at today
seems to give us some pointers. And I
will use that passage as a model for you
and for me
to help us navigate through some of the
crisis we face maybe
on a daily basis, on a weekly basis,
perhaps even on a monthly basis.
You look at what that passage is talking
about.
It mentions a father
who is about to lose his only daughter.
But it also, in the process of
mentioning a father, superimposed
in that story is a woman who had been
subject to bleeding for 12 years.
And then, the girl's
mother
is mentioned toward the very end of the
passage. Around verse 50 51 there, you
realize that she's mentioned only once,
and then alluded to at the very last
portion of that text.
So, you come to this passage and you
look at it and you realize that Jesus is
introduced. We are told that when Jesus
returned returned from where? He's
coming back from solving another crisis.
He had just encountered a man that had
been beset by a legion of demons. He had
cast out those demons and they ended up
in a pig or in pigs and then he's coming
back because the people in that region
had told him to leave.
But, we are told that as the people in
that region told him to leave, the crowd
welcomed him as they were expecting him.
So, very quickly as we look through what
to do when in crisis, let me give you
four reasons or four things that we need
to do based on this text.
When we find ourselves in crisis, when
in crisis, remember first of all to
direct your prayers to Jesus Christ.
When in crisis, direct your prayers to
Jesus Christ. Verse 40 says,
"Now, when Jesus returned, a crowd
welcomed him for they were all expecting
him." Now,
a man named Jairus,
a ruler of the synagogue, came to him
and fell on his feet
pleading with him
because pleading with him
because he wanted Jesus to come to his
house, his 12-year daughter, only
daughter, was dying. That's what the
Bible says. So, you have a man named
Jairus who is pleading before the Lord
Jesus Christ, telling him to come to his
house because his only daughter, a girl
of about 12, was dying.
That's the first instance of someone who
is directing his prayers to Jesus
Christ. But there's a second instance.
We are told that while Jesus was on his
way, the crowd almost crushed him.
And a woman was there who had been
subject to bleeding for 12 years and no
one could heal her.
If you notice,
you look at the same story in the book
of Mark or in the book of Matthew.
We are told that in those two instances,
this woman had sought help from doctors,
but she did not succeed in finding
healing.
Interestingly enough,
Luke does not mention that
because Luke was a doctor.
And maybe he did not want to present
himself in bad light. We don't know.
But here he is saying, "No one could
heal her."
And then she came up behind Jesus
and touched the edge of his cloak. And
immediately, the Bible says, her
bleeding stopped. So you have someone
who is verbally voicing his prayers to
Jesus Christ, and then you have another
person, a lady, who is silently
and almost secretly
demonstrating her prayers to Jesus
Christ by touching the edge of his
cloak. The Bible really does tell us, if
you read the
the book of Numbers 15 and the book of
Deuteronomy 22, that
every Jew
had to wear tassels in their garments.
And those tassels embedded in them, were
the commandments of the Lord that were
reminders of what the Lord wanted them
to do, of the rules and the laws of the
Lord.
And the only person allowed to touch the
tassel in Jewish tradition was somebody
who was closest to you if you are a Jew.
The person who was most intimately
related to you if you were a Jew. No one
else was allowed to touch the tassel.
Notice that the woman broke just about
every law in the book because since she
was subject to bleeding,
scripture, or at least the Jewish
scriptures, required that she remained
secluded. She was unclean and would not
touch anybody, and by touching the
people, she became
a person who was, quote unquote, making
them unclean.
And then she touches a tassel
that only somebody deeply related with
Jesus was allowed to touch. She directed
her prayers to Jesus Christ.
It was in 2018 when I was sitting on my
pa- at my pastoral desk in Orlando,
Florida.
And as I was preparing the sermon for
Sunday, it was a Thursday, as I was
preparing the sermon for Sunday, this
woman walked in and she said,
"Are you the preacher here?"
I said, "I'm afraid so."
And then she said, "Hey, listen.
My son is in hospital in the city of
Orlando.
I'm asking you to please go visit him. I
don't believe in God at all. In fact,
I'm not a religious person, but I want
you to go and pray for my son-in-law."
And I said, "Wait a minute. Wait a
minute. You don't believe in God?" She
says, "No, I don't." And you want me to
go and pray to the God you don't believe
in?"
She says, "Exactly. So, go to the
hospital and pray for my son-in-law." I
said, "Wait a minute. I don't understand
this.
If you don't believe in God, why would
you want me to pray?"
She said,
"I just don't, but I want you to go."
I said, "Okay." I took a pen and piece
of paper and I told her, "Give me the
name of the hospital."
She says, "I don't know the hospital he
is in."
I said, "Okay. Let's back up a little
bit here. You don't know the hospital,
you don't believe in God, and you want
me to go and pray for your son-in-law to
a God you don't believe in in a hospital
you don't know its location."
She says, "Exactly. I want you to go." I
said, "I don't understand it. There's
scores of hospitals in Orlando.
How am I even going to find the right
one?" She says, "Just go."
So, I said, "Okay." So, the following
day I got up in the morning and drove to
Orlando, the city of Orlando. It has
about six, maybe seven big hospitals,
actually a little more than that. And I
said, "Let me go to the one that seems
to be farthest and work my way
backwards."
So, I went to the hospital that I
thought was farthest,
parked my car,
went to the front desk, and I said, "Is
so-and-so
admitted in this hospital by any
chance?"
They looked up their records and they
said, "Oh, yeah, he's here."
And I said, "Okay. Miracle number one."
I said, "Okay, where is he?" "Eighth
floor. Just go on bed number so-and-so,
you'll find him." So, I got onto the
elevator, all the way to the eighth
floor.
And as soon as I walked into that room,
Mr. so-and-so looks at me and says, "Can
I help you?" I said, "Actually, I'm
coming here to help you."
And then she said he says,
"Uh
what do you want?" I said, "Your
mother-in-law sent me to you. I am
Pastor Joseph. Your mother-in-law sent
me to you to pray for you."
She says, "That's strange. She doesn't
believe in God at all. Why would she
send you to me?" I said, "I don't know,
but let's pray since this is what I'm
here to do." I asked him, "How are you
doing?" He said, "I'm not doing well. In
fact, I think I might just be dying."
So I said, "Hey, listen. Let's pray
together and trust the Lord to do
whatever he he does as God." So we held
hands and as I was praying, I felt
compelled to give him the book of Exodus
chapter 14 verse 14. I told him, "Hey,
please read that passage. I think
you might have a message in there for
you from the Lord."
So he's he wrote it on a tissue paper
and then he quickly looked for his Bible
and it said, "The Lord will fight for
you. You need only to be still."
After we prayed, I told him, "Hey,
listen. I'm not asking to become a
member of my church. All I'm asking you
to do is
when the Lord heals you, please make a
point of coming to church to tell me the
Lord did it. Would you please do that?"
He said, "Oh yeah, I'll do that for
you." So I walked away.
Sunday, I was preaching. His mother came
to church and she was sitting on my
peripheral view on the side and when I
was done preaching, she comes to me and
tells me, "That was a great sermon.
Thank you so much." and she walks away.
The next Sunday, she comes again to
church, sits next to some of the friends
there on my peripheral view and then
when I was done preaching, she comes to
me and said tells me, "Thank you so
much. That was a great sermon."
The third Sunday, as service begins, in
walks this tall gentleman smiling from
ear to ear and I recognized them as the
Mr. So-and-so that I'd gone to see. He
looks at me and smiles and he says,
"God did it."
That's what he said.
And all this to say,
when in crisis,
direct your prayers to Jesus Christ.
Before you call your doctor,
before you call your lawyer,
before you call your pastor,
before you call your counselor,
direct your prayers to Jesus Christ
because he
and he alone
is able to handle that problem in ways
that no one else can.
The second
thing that I want to share with you is,
when in crisis, not only would you
direct your prayers to Jesus Christ,
but demonstrate your patience with Jesus
Christ.
Demonstrate your patience with Jesus
Notice what is going on there.
We are told in verse 43
that after the woman had touched the hem
of his garment in verse 44, Jesus asked,
"Who touched me?"
When they all denied it,
Peter said, "Master,
the people are crowding and pressing
against you."
And Jesus replies and says, "Someone
touched me because I know power has come
out from me."
Then the woman,
seeing that she could not go
unnoticed,
came trembling and fell at Jesus' feet.
In the presence of all the people,
she told why she had touched him
and how she had been instantly healed.
All that is going on, put yourself in
the shoes of Jairus. His daughter is
about to die. Jesus is beginning his
walk towards Jairus's house and the
crowd, we are told, is crush almost
crushing him. That is an instance of
consternation therefore him. He's a
little impatient about that and then a
woman interrupts the process,
violates every rule and every law he
could think of at that time, touches a
tassel that she should not be touching
and his daughter is dying.
And then Jesus, rather than continue, he
stops.
And he asks, "Who touched me?"
It's obvious people are touching you,
maybe Jairus is saying, "Keep going."
And Jesus says, "Someone touched me. I
know someone touched me because power
has gone out of me."
It is very possible for such a situation
to test your patience. This happened to
me about a week and a half ago.
I had gone to a Safaricom shop to get
myself
a cell phone number.
And they made you you know the drill,
they make you sit there, they give you a
number and I sat there for about an
hour.
After an hour is when I was called to go
to counter number three.
So, I went to counter number three
and I told the lady what I needed
and then she said, "This will only take
20 minutes."
I sat there for about an hour
again.
And as I'm sitting there, I'm beginning
to get very impatient
and something is telling me, "You need
to give this lady a piece of your mind.
She is wasting your time. You've been
sitting here for 2 hours. This is
something they can do in 20 minutes. She
promised she would do in 20 minutes.
Look.
It is now an hour past the time she
promised you she would do this.
Come on, speak. Speak up.
And the lady finally solved the problem
and said, "This is your phone. This is
your number.
And by the way, I know you. You're
Pastor Joseph Okello."
And I really enjoy your sermons.
Imagine how she would have felt about me
if I gave her a piece of my mind.
All the sermons I've preached to her
will go to the trash.
And she will never care about me just
because I was impatient in a moment of a
tiny little crisis.
When in crisis, demonstrate your
patience with Jesus Christ. Even when
you're caught up in a traffic jam, be
patient.
Even when you're standing in line at the
bank,
be patient. When you pray and you're
waiting for an answer, sister so-and-so
prays and she instantly gets an answer.
You're still waiting for yours. Be
patient.
When in crisis,
direct your prayers to Jesus Christ.
Demonstrate your patience with Jesus
Christ. Reason number three, or the
third thing you and I need to do is to
display our faith in Jesus.
Verse 45.
Jesus looks at this woman
and he says, "Daughter,
your faith has healed you.
Go in peace." And while he's still
speaking, the Bible says
someone from Jairus' house, the
synagogue ruler, comes and says, "Your
daughter is dead. Don't bother the
teacher anymore." And Jesus again speaks
and says, "Don't be afraid. Just believe
and she will be healed." Those are two
instances that Jesus is demanding that
we demonstrate our faith in him. Go back
to where Jesus tells that lady,
"Daughter, your faith has healed you."
Do you notice that in verse 43, she's
introduced as a woman
who breaks every rule, breaks every
Jewish law that she could think of at
that time, touches the tassel that she's
not supposed to touch,
and Jesus calls her
daughter.
From woman, who is not supposed to be
related to me
as a family, to daughter. Meaning that
Jesus had accepted her as a member of
his family. That's what faith does to
you.
You know,
faith is basically taking God at his
word.
All you've got is not faith
until faith is all you've got.
I know this
quite well.
My wife was diagnosed with breast cancer
10 years ago.
And you know, I have been preaching have
faith, have faith.
God's going to heal you. Have faith.
Until cancer knocked at my door.
And then I asked myself, "Do I really
now believe what I've been preaching to
everybody else?"
Do I really trust this God that I've
been telling everybody? I went on a 21
day of fasting.
Calling on the name of the Lord, have
mercy on my wife, have mercy on my son,
have mercy on my family. Lord, have
mercy.
Calling on the name of the Lord.
Today, she's cancer-free.
Not because of me, please understand.
But because of who God is.
Have faith in God.
Display your faith in Jesus Christ.
The fourth and final idea here is, when
in crisis
direct your prayers to Jesus Christ.
Demonstrate your patience with Jesus.
Display your faith in Jesus and derive
your power from Jesus Christ.
We are told, beginning at around verse
50, 51, when Jesus arrived at Jairus'
house.
The Bible says, he would not let anyone
go in with him
except Peter, John, and James and the
child's father and mother. That's the
first time the mother is mentioned.
Meanwhile, the people were crying
and wailing
and mourning for her.
"Stop wailing," Jesus said, "she's not
dead but asleep." And they laughed at
him knowing that she was dead.
And he continues to say here that Jesus
took her hand and said, "My child, get
up." Her spirit returned, she got up
at once
and began to walk.
And Jesus
asked them to give her something to eat
and then her parents were astonished.
But Jesus ordered them not to tell
anyone what had happened.
This is what deriving your power from
God does. It begins with prayer.
And then, some patience involved. And
then, faith.
Those three
bring in the power of Jesus. That's
where you derive your power from Jesus
Christ.
And as I was thinking about this,
and I was thinking about what our
sisters have done in this congregation
and in this church, and as they were
singing,
quite frankly, I did not want for them
to stop.
That's when you know you're really
worshipping, when you don't want it to
stop. You just want it to continue. And
as I was thinking about the men, the
fathers,
who raised children and become role
models for their children.
As I was thinking about this, I said,
"How can I describe their ministry? What
God has done for them from the time that
he
he saved their souls through the death
of Jesus Christ on the cross and his
resurrection on the third day?" How can
I describe the ministry of our sisters
and the ministries of our fathers? I was
thinking of the letters A through Z.
The when you begin with a letter A,
they're agents of the almighty.
They're believers of the Bible.
They're carriers of the cross.
They're defeaters of the devil.
They're examples of excellence.
They're fighters of the faith.
They're guardians of the gospel.
They're houses of honor.
They're instances of integrity.
They have the joy of Jesus.
They have the kindness of the king.
They are laborers
of the Lord.
They are messengers of the Messiah.
They are nominators of the numinous.
They are offsprings of omnipotent
omnipotence.
They are questers
of quality.
They are preachers of the prince of
peace. They are reflections of the
redeemer.
They are servants of the savior.
They are teachers of the truth.
They are umpires of unity.
They are voices of virtue.
They are witnesses of the word.
They are X factors of xenophiliacs.
They are youthful for Yahweh.
And they are zealous for Zion.
>> [applause]
>> But how do I even go ahead and describe
this God? Let me stretch your brain a
little.
Because now I'm not going to go from A
to Z. I'm going to go from Z to A.
So when you're thinking of this God,
this Jesus, this Lord that we worship
every Sunday, that you pray to every
morning,
and whose word you read every day,
you become to realize that he's
infinitely zesty.
He's infinitely Yahweh.
He's infinitely genial.
He's infinitely wonderful. He's
infinitely virtuous. He's infinitely
unsurpassable.
He's infinitely trustworthy.
He's infinitely
sovereign.
reliable.
He's infinitely quick-witted.
He's infinitely powerful.
He's infinitely omnibenevolent.
He's infinitely numinous. He's
infinitely mighty.
He's infinitely loving. He's infinitely
kind. He's infinitely just. He's
infinitely
immortal. He's infinitely holy. He's
infinitely generous. He's infinitely
faithful. He's infinitely excellent.
He's infinitely dependable. He's
infinitely capable. He's infinitely
believable. And he's infinitely able.
>> [applause]
>> And when you come to him,
you realize that he's so different
from human beings.
When you think of a pilot,
even the best pilot will crash a plane.
Could crash a plane.
Even the best lawyer could lose a case.
Even the best doctor could lose a
patient.
Even the best soldier could lose the
war. But Jesus Christ is a doctor who's
never lost a patient.
He's a lawyer
>> [applause and music]
>> who's never lost a case.
He's a pilot who always lands his plane.
And he's a warrior who always wins the
battle.
And that is the God that I worship.
That is the God that you worship. May I
suggest to you to continue worshiping
him. When in crisis, remember
to direct your prayers to Jesus Christ,
to demonstrate your patience with Jesus
Christ, [music]
to decipher
and display your faith in Jesus Christ,
and to draw your power
from Jesus Christ.
Take that home with you.
Amen.